Guide to the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences records
1799-1987
MS 1373
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.5
(21 boxes)
The records consist of minutes of meetings, financial records, correspondence, exchange agreements, and publications arrangements which document the founding and continuous activities of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences. The records also contain data gathered by the academy, during the early nineteenth century, on weather, population, health, and geography.
Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1992.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. General Records, 1799-1986. II. Membership, 1870-1983. III. Publications, 1871-1984. Subject Files, 1800-1949.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences include its constitution, minutes of meetings, financial records, correspondence, exchange agreements and publications arrangements. The records also contain data gathered during the early nineteenth century on weather, population, health and geography.
Although the records of the Academy were formally donated to the University Library in 1992, a trunk of its early records was first deposited in the Rare Book Room of the Library in 1938. In 1992, the Academy added material up to the 1980s and indicated its intention to continue to do so in the future.
The records are arranged in four series: I. General Records, 1799-1986; II. Membership, 1870-1983; III. Publications, 1871-1984; and Subject Files, 1800-1949. Oversize materials for all series are arranged at the end of the records.
Series I, GENERAL RECORDS, contains correspondence, record books, and other papers beginning with the formation of the Academy. The series includes the Academy's charter, constitution and by-laws, financial accounts, and records of meetings.
The correspondence files date from 1799 to 1985. The nineteenth century correspondence contains discussions of the mission and the constitution of the Academy, the assignment of tasks for collecting data and descriptions of findings. There are acknowledgements of learned institutions receiving copies of a medal struck by the Academy to celebrate the New Haven bicentennial and of publications of the Academy, acceptances by individuals to membership when associated with other Academy business, and obituary notices. There is little correspondence for the last three decades.
The correspondence of the twentieth century is largely routine dealing with authors interested in publication, arrangements for meetings, and invitations to speakers. Correspondence with other learned societies about meetings and celebrations is included under "Academic Societies."
Record books (folders 121-128) contain minutes of the Academy and council meetings, membership lists and financial records. These books are varied rather than consistent in arrangement. Each book may contain one or more of these types of records. Although the record book covering 1881 to 1949 mentions a volume titled "Council 1872-1881" and the intention of continuing those minutes on page 375 of the same volume, no notes are found there. There is some mention of the Publication Committee in 1886. The available volume of the Publication Committee's minutes begins in 1907. From November 13, 1944, the meetings are designated as those of the council. The discussions include policy matters as well as publications. For 1970 there is an additional folder of minutes from Publication Committee meetings (folder 172). Council meetings are recorded in a volume dated 1872-1881 (folder 123) and in a volume dated 1907-1965 (folder 76) as well as in loose files (folders 77-79) from 1965 through 1986.
Financial records start with a cash book dated 1799-1899 with an additional folder from 1840 to 1985. A treasurer's book lists members' contributions made between 1799 and 1825. Records from the Yale University Treasurer's Office spanning 1908-1938 show income and expenditures for each fiscal year.
Details of meetings are described not only in the record books but also in the folders labeled "Notices, correspondence, etc." dated 1965-1986. Records of special meetings, such as the thousandth meeting in 1949 and the centennial anniversary in 1899, are in separate folders.
Series II, MEMBERSHIP, includes lists and registers of members. Additional membership information is available in the record books of GENERAL RECORDS. There are many routine letters of acceptance, resignation and declination. The files of "Correspondence, lists, notes" contain membership lists, membership totals, and address lists.
Series III, PUBLICATIONS, contains correspondence concerning individual publications as well as correspondence with dealers, printers and distributors. Records for individual publications (roughly ten per cent of the total publications) are filed under the name of the author, followed by the initial of the publication (T for Transactions, M for Memoirs ) and the volume number in Roman numerals. Information available about the exchange of Academy publications for those of other academic societies from 1916-1983 is arranged chronologically. Some publications inventory lists from 1851 to 1984 are included.
Series IV, SUBJECT FILES, contains data collected by academy members in the early to mid-nineteenth century. The data include meteorological registers of New Haven and Washington, D.C., census data, bills of mortality for various cities, statistical data on New Haven and New London, observations on meteors and on the variation of the magnetic needle. From 1800 to 1830, barometric readings plus notes were recorded for every day. The minutes intimate that recordings were also made between 1830 and 1840 but these are lacking. The project was resumed from 1840 to 1852.
The series also contains other observations, including a folder of papers, given by the Reverend D. A. Sherman in 1829, of work by various investigators on the exploration of old fortifications and burial grounds in Tennessee and near the Mississippi River, a nineteenth century paper by Robert Stevenson on centripetal force and a folder of various papers by Noah Webster Jr., circa 1780, discussing St. Vitus Dance, maize and other corn, a light phenomenon similar to the Aurora Borealis, and customs and language of the Sandwich Islands. The Miscellaneous file contains thoughts on the nature and origin of knowledge, chemical experiments regarding the coloring principle of Prussian blue, a discussion of inherited characteristics and an essay on evaporation.
Biographical / Historical
The Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences was founded in 1799 in New Haven. The goal of the academy is to represent the arts, the humanities, and the sciences in the state through its meetings and publications. It publishes Memoirs and Transactions. The academy continues to hold several meetings a year at various academic institutions around the state.
The constitution of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences declares that "The object of this Academy is to cultivate every art and science which may tend to advance the interest and happiness of a free and virtuous people." Over the years it has been the goal of the Academy to represent the arts, the humanities and the sciences in Connecticut through its meetings and publications.
In 1779, the year after Ezra Stiles became president of Yale College, he proposed the founding of a learned society in Connecticut that would embrace the purposes of the American Philosophical Society which had been established by Benjamin Franklin in 1769. Stiles discussed the project with Benjamin Guild of Harvard who, with his associates, founded the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in 1780, but a Connecticut society was politically untimely and would not come to fruition until 1799, four years after Timothy Dwight had succeeded Stiles as president of Yale College.
One of the first activities of the Academy was to issue a statewide circular in January 1800 requesting comprehensive information for a proposed "Statistical Account of Towns and Parishes in the State of Connecticut." This was Timothy Dwight's idea, and he produced a masterful pamphlet on the statistics of New Haven which was published by the Academy in 1811. Materials on other towns continued to be received until 1827, but the project was never completed and nothing more was ever published. Meteorology also commanded the attention of the Academy from its earliest days. In 1800, the Academy began recording meteorological observations for New Haven, a practice that it would support for more than fifty years.
From 1810 to 1816 the Academy published 25 papers in the first volume of its new journal, Memoirs. In 1818, the Academy abandoned publication of Memoirs when Benjamin Silliman the elder inaugurated the new American Journal of Science, which provided a frequent and regular medium of publication. However, the Academy later found that it had available a considerable amount of material which was not deemed suitable for publication in the American Journal of Science. Thus Transactions, a new series of publications, was inaugurated in 1866. The early issues of the Transactions also listed officers and members of committees as well as additions to the Academy library by gift and exchange at the beginning of each volume.
Silliman served as president of the Academy from 1836 to 1847. During this time the Academy became intellectually and emotionally involved with the dramatic affair of the Spanish slave ship Amistad and its mutinous captives. While the captives were awaiting trial in the New Haven jail in 1839, one of the Academy members, Josiah Willard Gibbs the elder, used his knowledge of philology and his resourcefulness to develop a means of conversing with the Africans so that their side of the story could be told. The Africans were eventually freed by the U.S. Supreme Court and were repatriated in 1841 - the only such captives ever to escape permanent servitude and to return home.
After Silliman's presidency there followed a period of decline, and the Academy sold its library and voted to deposit unpublished manuscripts of the statistical accounts in the Connecticut Historical Society. Although attendance at meetings decreased, important scientific advances were presented at meetings and the best of the communications did appear in print to reach a wider audience. The third volume of the Transactions of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences gave the world the study by Josiah Willard Gibbs the younger, "On the Equilibrium of Heterogeneous Substances" (October 1875-May 1876 and May 1877-July 1878) which provided the basis for physical chemistry. After an enthusiastic celebration of the Academy's centennial in 1899, the attendance again declined, but the Transactions continued to appear at the rate of a volume or two every two or three years.
In the nineteenth century, the meetings and publications had been primarily concerned with the natural and physical sciences. An agreement between the Academy and Yale in 1906 brought financial aid for increased publication and encouraged the Academy to widen its range of interests; papers were subsequently presented on history, economics, philosophy, linguistics, and belle-lettres in addition to continuing communications in biology, geology, chemistry, physics and engineering.
After George Eaton became secretary of the Academy in 1907, publication of the Transactions was accelerated and in 1910 the Memoirs of the Academy reappeared, this time in quarto form for major illustrated works. Eaton added editorial work to his other duties and continued in office until 1946, a remarkable record of devoted service sustaining a steady tradition through two wars and many academic changes.
In addition to Memoirs and Transactions, the Academy undertook a special publication, "A Manual of the Writings in Middle English, 1050-1500" edited by John Edwin Wells (1916). The manual became a standard reference tool and continues to be supplemented.
The Academy was able to distribute its publications more widely through an agreement with the Yale University Library. The Library gave the Academy an annual subvention for publications which the Library used in its exchange program with other institutions. This support continues. By 1973 the Academy's library was given to Yale University.
In 1954 the Academy joined with the Connecticut Science Teachers' Association to sponsor an annual High School Sciences Talent Search in Connecticut. This project took place during the long and dedicated service of Dorothea Rudnick as secretary of the Academy. She took office at the 978th meeting in October, 1946 and served as secretary through September, 1986.
The Academy was always intimately associated with Yale and for the first 150 years its meetings were held at a variety of locations in New Haven. Thus its active members were only those living within a convenient distance of New Haven who could attend meetings and cast their vote. In the early 1950s, the council discussed the desirability of encouraging more participation from other institutions in Connecticut, and in 1952 the Academy convened a meeting at Storrs to welcome new members from the University of Connecticut. On the occasion of the 175th anniversary of the Academy in 1974 a meeting was held at Wesleyan University; Southern Connecticut State University was added in 1984 and Trinity College in 1991.
For additional details on the history of the Academy up to 1949, consult the Rollin G. Osterweis "Sesquicentennial History of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences" in its Transactions, volume 38, pages 103-149 upon which this summary is based.
Demographic surveys -- Connecticut; Meteorology; Science -- History; Science -- Societies, etc. -- Connecticut; Connecticut -- Learned institutions and societies; Demographic records; Meteorological records; George Eaton; Dorthea Rudnick; Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences
- GENERAL RECORDS, 1799-1986; Series I; 3.75' (9 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The material in this series is arranged by record types and is listed in alphabetical order. Within the record type the arrangement is chronological.
  - Charter amendment, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1799-1845 (Box 1, Folder 4-10)
    - General, 1846-1849 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      General
      See also: box 21, folder 293
    - General, 1850-1899, 1905-1921 (Box 1, Folder 12-22)
    - General, 1922-1966 (Box 2, Folder 23-44)
    - General, 1967-1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 45-66)
    - Academic societies, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Academic societies: solicatations for assistance, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Celebration for Dorothea Rudnick's eightieth birthday, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Invitations to other academies' celebrations, 1906-1965 (Box 4, Folder 70-72)
    - One hundred and seventy-fifth anniversary exhibit, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Science talent search, 1955-1966 (Box 4, Folder 74-75)
  - Council/publication meeting, 1907-1965 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Council meetings, 1965-1969 (Box 4, Folder 77-78)
  - Council meetings, 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    See also:box 13, folder 172
  - Council meetings, 1976-1980 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Council meetings, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Financial records
    - Cash book, 1799-1899 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - General, 1840-1950 (Box 5, Folder 83-95)
    - General, 1951-1985 (Box 6, Folder 96-104)
    - Treasurer's book, 1799-1825 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - University treasurer's office, 1908-1938 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Lists of officers and of members, 1919-1984 (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - Meetings
    - Centennial anniversary, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Centennial anniversary, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 109)
      See also: box 21, folder 294
    - Notices, correspondence, etc., 1965-1986, undated (Box 7, Folder 110-116)
    - Thousandth meeting: delegates, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - Thousandth meeting: greetings, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - Thousandth meeting: invitations, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - Thousandth meeting: program, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Record book, 1799-1858, 1858 January-1881 January (Box 8, Folder 121-122)
  - Record book: council minutes only, 1872-1881 (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Record book, 1881 January-1949 April (Box 9, Folder 124)
  - Record book: minutes and register of members, 1949 May-1986 (Box 9, Folder 125)
  - Record books: associated loose documents, 1833, undated, 1881 January-1949 March, 1949 May-1986 (Box 9, Folder 126-128)
- MEMBERSHIP, 1870-1987; Series II; 1.25' (3 boxes)
  The material in this series is arranged by record type and is listed in alphabetical order. Within the record type the arrangement is chronological.
  - Acceptances, 1905-1965 (Box 10, Folder 129-145)
  - Correspondence, lists, notes, etc., 1955-1973 (Box 10, Folder 146-148)
  - Correspondence, lists, notes, etc., 1974-1987 (Box 11, Folder 149-158)
  - List of members, Circa 1870s-1880 (Box 11, Folder 159)
  - List of members: with taxes paid, compiled annually, 1884-1911 (Box 12, Folder 160)
  - List of members, 1911-1940s (Box 12, Folder 161)
  - Necrology, 1903-1965 (Box 12, Folder 162)
  - Register of members, 1949-1957 (Box 12, Folder 163)
  - Resignations and declinations, 1904-1930 (Box 12, Folder 164-167)
  - Resignations, 1931-1968 (Box 12, Folder 168-171)
- PUBLICATIONS, 1871-1984; Series III; 2.25' (5 boxes)
  The material in this series is arranged by record type. The files of correspondence concerning individual publications are arranged by the last name of the author. The files of correspondence with publishers/dealers are arranged by the name of the firm and chronologically within those sets. The files of exchanges are arranged chronologically.
  - Committee meetings, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 172)
    See also: box 4, folder 79
  - Correspondence concerning individual publications
    - Bidwell TXX, 1916 (Box 13, Folder 173)
    - Christopherson TXVII, 1922-1937 (Box 13, Folder 174)
    - Clark TXXIV, 1910-1914 (Box 13, Folder 175)
    - Clark, 1915-1921 (Box 13, Folder 176)
    - Cowgill MXVII, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 177)
    - Deevey TXXXIX, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 178)
    - Donaldson TXXXIX, 1955 (Box 13, Folder 179)
    - Dunham TXXXIX, 1955 (Box 13, Folder 180)
    - Dzulynski TXLII, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 181)
    - Eaton/Bingham, 1915-1922 (Box 13, Folder 182)
    - Evans TXXXVIII, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 183)
    - Ferris TXXV, 1919-1921 (Box 13, Folder 184)
    - Gause TXXXVII, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 185)
    - Gill TXXXII, 1934-1935 (Box 13, Folder 186)
    - Hessler MXVI, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 187)
    - Ingholt MXII, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 188)
    - Kubler MXI, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 189)
    - Latourette TXXII, 1916-1917 (Box 13, Folder 190)
    - MacCurdy MIII, 1921-1950 (Box 13, Folder 191)
    - Mathewson TXXXVIII #7, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 192)
    - Means TXXI, 1917-1921 (Box 13, Folder 193)
    - Miller TXXXI, 1931-1932 (Box 13, Folder 194)
    - Nemoy TXL, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 195)
    - Obermann TXXXVIII, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 196)
    - Osterweis (photos) TXXXVIII, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 197)
    - Pentrunkevitch TXXXVI, 1945 (Box 14, Folder 198)
    - Pentrunkevitch TXXXVII, 1949 (Box 14, Folder 199)
    - Pentrunkevitch TXLI, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 200)
    - Raymond MVII, 1916-1921 (Box 14, Folder 201)
    - Sanders MX5, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 202)
    - Shufeldt TXIX, 1914 (Box 14, Folder 203)
    - Szöverffy TXLII, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 204)
    - Thieme TXLI, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 205)
    - Vernadsky TXXXI, 1933 (Box 14, Folder 206)
    - Verrill TXXVI, 1922-1923 (Box 14, Folder 207)
    - Wells Manual, 1915-1953 (Box 14, Folder 208-212)
    - Wells Manual, 1954-1975 (Box 15, Folder 213-214)
    - Wells Manual, reviews, undated (Box 15, Folder 215)
    - Winslow TXXXII, 1932-1934 (Box 15, Folder 216)
    - Yale North India Expedition, 1934-1957 (Box 15, Folder 217)
  - Correspondence with publishers and dealers
    - Biancos Lunos Bogtrykkeri, 1955-1966 (Box 15, Folder 218)
    - Kraus Reprint Corporation, 1966-1983 (Box 15, Folder 219)
    - Munksgaard, 1958-1964 (Box 15, Folder 220)
    - Shoestring Press, 1968-1978, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 221-230)
    - University Microfilms, 1964-1990 (Box 15, Folder 231)
    - Yale University Press, 1910-1942 (Box 15, Folder 232-238)
    - Yale University Press, 1954-1986 (Box 16, Folder 239)
  - Exchanges, 1916-1975 (Box 16, Folder 240-249)
  - Exchanges: reports of the librarian, 1920-1983 (Box 16, Folder 250-253)
  - Exchanges: Yale Library subvention, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 254)
  - Gifts to war devastated and other libraries, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 255)
  - Inventories, 1951-1984, undated (Box 16, Folder 256-259)
  - Lists, undated (Box 17, Folder 260)
  - Permissions, undated (Box 17, Folder 261)
  - Standing orders, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 262)
  - Subscriptions for the continuance of the publication of Transactions of the Connecticut Academy, 1871, 1872, 1883, 1903 (Box 17, Folder 263)
  - Unidentified illustrations
    See: box 21, folder 295
- SUBJECT FILES, 1800-1949; Series IV; 1.25' (3 boxes)
  The material in this series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Bills of mortality: communities, undated (Box 18, Folder 264-265)
  - Barometric measurements: Hartford, 1816 (Box 18, Folder 266)
  - Census of New Haven
    See: box 21, folder 296
  - Connecticut: proposals for a statistical history, 1800 (Box 18, Folder 267)
  - Histories of the Connecticut Academy, 1839, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 268)
  - Meteorological data: Wallingford
    See: box 21, folders 298-299
  - Meteorological register: New Haven, 1800 March-1820 December (Box 18, Folder 269-271)
  - Meteorological register: New Haven, 1821 January-1830 Nov, 1840 December-1852 April (Box 19, Folder 272-277)
  - Meteorological register: Washington, D.C., 1802 (Box 19, Folder 278)
  - New Haven data: occupations; geography; botany; zoology; manufactures, undated (Box 20, Folder 279)
  - New Haven data, undated (Box 20, Folder 280-281)
    See also: box 21, folder 297
  - Observations of meteors: New Haven, 1861 September 9 (Box 20, Folder 282)
  - On the variation of the magnetic needle, undated (Box 20, Folder 283-287)
    See also:box 21, folder 300
  - Sherman, Rev. D. A.: papers given by, 1829 (Box 20, Folder 288)
    See also: box 21, folder 301
  - Statistical Account of New London: paper, undated (Box 20, Folder 289)
  - Stevenson: paper, undated (Box 20, Folder 290)
  - Webster, Noah Jr.: papers, 1780 (Box 20, Folder 291)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1803-1842 (Box 20, Folder 292)
    See also: box 21, folder 302
- OVERSIZE
  - Correspondence and financial records, 1840-1849 (Box 21, Folder 293)
  - Centennial anniversary, 1899 (Box 21, Folder 294)
  - Publications: unidentified illustrations, undated (Box 21, Folder 295)
  - Census of New Haven, 1800 (Box 21, Folder 296)
  - New Haven data, Circa 1810 (Box 21, Folder 297)
  - Meteorological data: wind charts, Wallingford, 1851-1862 (Box 21, Folder 298)
  - Meteorological data: photographs of Wallingford tornado, undated (Box 21, Folder 299)
  - On the variations of the magnetic needle, undated (Box 21, Folder 300)
  - Sherman, Rev. D. A.: papers given by, 1829 (Box 21, Folder 301)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1842 (Box 21, Folder 302)